Guide to the Vassar College Wimpfheimer Nursery School Records, approximately 1927-2009
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Wimpfheimer Nursery School Records
approximately 1927-2009
Vassar College Wimpfheimer Nursery School
79 cubic feet (79 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The records consist of administrative files for the nursery school as well as the Child Study Department; student records for undergraduate students working in the nursery school or taking coursework in the Child Study or Psychology departments; and files on children who attended the nursery school.
Biographical Note
The Wimpfheimer Nursery school opened in 1927. It was funded by the father of Mildred R. Wimpfheimer, Vassar Class of 1927, and bears her name. The school was founded not only as an educational institution, but also as a "living laboratory" for classes in euthenics and psychology.
Scope and Content Note
The records consist of administrative files for the nursery school as well as the Child Study Department; student records for undergraduate students working in the nursery school or taking coursework in the Child Study or Psychology departments; and student records of children who attended the nursery school.
Access
The student records in this collection are closed to research due to privacy issues. The Administrative records are open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
This collection is stored off-site and requires advance notification for use. If ordered Monday-Thursday we can generally guarantee delivery for the next day. Please contact the
Library Staff
for more information.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College. Department of Child Study; Vassar College. Department of Psychology
Subjects:
Child psychology; Nursery schools
Document Types:
Administrative records; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Special Programs and Projects
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, April 2010. Updated by Mark Seidl, March 2014. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, August 2023.
Acquisition Information
Transferred in several accessions: the first at an unknown date, the second in 2006, the third in 2014, and the fourth in 2023.
Accruals
Further accessions expected at regular intervals.
Series List
- Series I. Undergraduate Students [RESTRICTED], 1940-2004
- Series II. Nursery School Children [RESTRICTED], circa 1927-2009
- Series III. Administrative Records, 1927-1995
Container List
- Series I. Undergraduate Students [RESTRICTED], 1940-2004
  - A-Bena, 1940-2004 (Box 1)
  - Benj-Byr, 1940-2004 (Box 2)
  - C-Dav, 1940-2004 (Box 3)
  - Daw-Far, 1940-2004 (Box 4)
  - Fas-Get, 1940-2004 (Box 5)
  - Gia-Harr, 1940-2004 (Box 6)
  - Hart-Hyn, 1940-2004 (Box 7)
  - I-Kyr, 1940-2004 (Box 8)
  - L-Mar, 1940-2004 (Box 9)
  - Mai-Mo, 1940-2004 (Box 10)
  - Mu-Pi, 1940-2004 (Box 11)
  - Pl-R, 1940-2004 (Box 12)
  - S-Sp, 1940-2004 (Box 13)
  - St-To, 1940-2004 (Box 14)
  - Tr-We, 1940-2004 (Box 15)
  - Wh-Z, 1940-2004 (Box 79)
  - Marist Students, 1986-1988 (Box 73)
  - Research Files, circa 1990-1999 (Box 73)
  - Vassar Students, 1955-1959; [1 folder] (Box 79)
  - Vassar Students, 1991-1993 (Box 73)
- Series II. Nursery School Children [RESTRICTED], circa 1927-2009
  - A-Bas, circa 1927-1990 (Box 16)
  - Bau-Brev, circa 1927-1990 (Box 17)
  - Brew-Car, circa 1927-1990 (Box 18)
  - Cas-Cook, circa 1927-1990 (Box 19)
  - Coom-Davi, circa 1927-1990 (Box 20)
  - Davy-Dou, circa 1927-1990 (Box 21)
  - Dow-Ef, circa 1927-1990 (Box 22)
  - Eh-Fil, circa 1927-1990 (Box 23)
  - Fin-Gar, circa 1927-1990 (Box 24)
  - Gat-Gou, circa 1927-1990 (Box 25)
  - Gra-Heal, circa 1927-1990 (Box 26)
  - Heat-How, circa 1927-1990 (Box 27)
  - His-Kauf, circa 1927-1990 (Box 28)
  - Kay-Lang, circa 1927-1990 (Box 29)
  - Lane-Lin, circa 1927-1990 (Box 30)
  - Lip-Mat, circa 1927-1990 (Box 31)
  - May-Mik, circa 1927-1990 (Box 32)
  - Mil-Nei, circa 1927-1990 (Box 33)
  - Nel-Pay, circa 1927-1990 (Box 34)
  - Pea-Rat, circa 1927-1990 (Box 35)
  - Ray-Roma, circa 1927-1990 (Box 36)
  - Rome-Rut, circa 1927-1990 (Box 37)
  - Rya-Schu, circa 1927-1990 (Box 38)
  - Schw-Smi, circa 1927-1990 (Box 39)
  - Smy-Sut, circa 1927-1990 (Box 40)
  - Swe-Ung, circa 1927-1990 (Box 41)
  - Usp-Way, circa 1927-1990 (Box 42)
  - Web-Wis, circa 1927-1990 (Box 43)
  - Wo-Zwe, circa 1927-1990 (Box 44)
  - Students, 1993 Sep - 1997 May (Box 67)
  - Students, 2001 Sep - 2005 Aug (Box 68)
  - Students, 2003 Sep - 2005 May (Box 72)
  - G-K, 1993 Sep - 2003 May (Box 69)
  - K-R, 1997 Sep - 2003 May (Box 70)
  - R-Z, 1995 Sep - 2003 May (Box 71)
  - Ma-Mi, 1979-1994 (Box 75)
  - Eb-Un, 1996 Sep -2009 May (Box 76)
  - Ba-Kr, 2002 Sep - 2008 May (Box 77)
  - Ma-Wi, 2001 Sep - 2008 May (Box 78)
- Series III. Administrative Records, 1927-1995
  - Afternoon Groups, 1965-1969 (Box 66)
  - Child Study Department, 1927-1933 (Box 45)
  - Child Study Department, 1933-1935 (Box 46)
  - Child Study Department, 1935-1936 (Box 47)
  - Child Study Department, 1936-1938 (Box 48)
  - Child Study Department, 1937-1942 (Box 49)
  - Child Study Department, 1941-1942 (Box 50)
  - Child Study Department, 1942-1945 (Box 51)
  - Child Study Department, 1942-1947 (Box 52)
  - Child Study Department, 1944-1947 (Box 53)
  - Child Study Department, 1945-1949 (Box 54)
  - Child Study Department, 1947-1950 (Box 55)
  - Child Study Department, 1949-1952 (Box 56)
  - Nursery School Files, 1948-1990 (Box 65)
  - Nursery School Files, 1951-1952 (Box 57)
  - Nursery School Files, 1951-1953 (Box 58)
  - Nursery School Files, 1952-1958 (Box 59)
  - Nursery School Files, 1957-1960 (Box 60)
  - Nursery School Files, 1959-1962 (Box 61)
  - Nursery School Files, 1961-1973 (Box 62)
  - Nursery School Files, 1971, 1973-1977 (Box 64)
  - Nursery School Files, 1977-1983 (Box 74)
  - Nursery School Files, 1979-1986 (Box 63)
  - Photographs: "Blocks Workshop," slides, 1969, 1974; [1 folder] (Box 79)
  - Photographs: Nursery School, negatives, 1968; [1 folder] (Box 79)
  - Photographs: Nursery School, "PM and AM Groups, #1-4," negatives, 1967 Fall; [1 folder] (Box 79)
  - Photographs: Nursery School and Dorothy Levens, prints, 1967 Oct; [1 folder] (Box 79)
  - Scholarships, 1989-1995 (Box 64)
  - Sketches of equipment designed for Nursery School (Originals), 1962; [1 folder] (Box 79)